<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael W. Kearney</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Michael W. Kearney</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© Michael W. Kearney 2017</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Position I&amp;rsquo;m an assistant professor at the University of Missouri where I hold a joint appointment in Journalism Studies with the School of Journalism and in Data Science and Analytics with the Informatics Institute. I teach courses in mass media, political communication, quantitative research methods, and data science.
Research My research uses computational social scientific methods to track the dissemination of information and better understand media selection behaviors in digital media environments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/links/</guid>
      <description>My links</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tweets about Mueller Investigation</title>
      <link>/post/2017/11/02/tweets-about-mueller-investigation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/11/02/tweets-about-mueller-investigation/</guid>
      <description>On Monday (Oct. 30th), the first charges were filed in the Mueller investigation on potential connections between the Trump campaign and the Kremlin. It’s major political news, so I wanted to capture as much of the relevant tweets as I could. In this post, I’ve documented the step-by-step of how I went about collecting the data.
1. Install and load rtweet Although I expect to update rtweet on CRAN very soon, the code below assumes the installed version of rtweet is at least version &#39;0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twitter APIs</title>
      <link>/post/2017/10/30/twitter-apis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017/10/30/twitter-apis/</guid>
      <description>Twitter data gatekeeping Even before the unpresidented Twitter-centric 2016 U.S. election, researchers flocked to Twitter data (Lee, Yoon, Smith, Park, &amp;amp; Park, 2017; Peoples, Midway, Sackett, Lynch, &amp;amp; Cooney, 2016; Priem &amp;amp; Costello, 2010; Shuai, Pepe, &amp;amp; Bollen, 2012). Why? Well, aside from the obvious–that it’s an immensely popular social media platform–Twitter attracts scholarly attention because it makes a lot of its data freely available to the public via Application Program Interfaces (APIs).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>